准备好了吗  孩子们
Are you ready, kids?
好了船长
Aye aye, captain
我听不见
I can't hear you
好了船长
Aye aye, captain
是谁住在深海的大菠萝里
Who lives in a pineapple under the sea?
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
方方黄黄伸缩自如
Absorbent and yellow and porous is he
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
如果四处探险是你的愿望
If nautical nonsense be something you wish
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
那就敲敲甲板让大鱼开路
Then drop on the deck and flop like a fish
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
准备
Ready
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
天才派大星
分镜总监
翻译: 1440kHz
编剧
技术总监
动画总监
制片指导
本字幕仅限学习交流
严禁用于商业用途
水母田
你当鬼
You're it
派大星  等等
Wait, Pat--
你当鬼
you're it
牌子
The sign
悬崖危险
派大星
Patrick
这就救你出来  兄弟
Let me help you out of there, buddy
你下半身还在那下面吗
Is the rest of you down there?
我下半身在这上面
The rest of me is up here
你害我担心死了  兄弟
You had me worried there, buddy
头给你
Here's your head
我发觉这些笑声毫无逻辑可言
I find all this laughter to be highly illogical
那就别笑了  来捉水母
Well, let's stop laughing and let's start fishing
你先来捉吧
Go ahead, you get first crack
看看它们
Look at them--
这些优雅又坚忍的海洋生物
these graceful stoic creatures of the deep
这话好高深  派大星
Those are some big words, Pat
以前没听过你这么说
I've never heard you use them before
荒谬  我的词汇量正无穷扩展中
Nonsense, my vocabulary is infinitely expanding
那咱来展开我们的水母网吧
Well, let's expand our jellyfish nets
来吧  派大星
Come on, Patrick
兄弟你看  我捉到一只了
Look, buddy, I captured one
是的  我同样绘制了一只
Yes, I captured one as well
捕 捉
而未干扰到其娇弱的生态系统
without disturbing its delicate ecosystem
如此野蛮地利用自然是错误的
It is wrong to harness nature in such a barbaric manner
好吧
Okay
你要干什么
What do you want to do?
一起去欣赏自然的美丽和脆弱
Let us go off and admire
the beauty and fragility of nature
好漂亮
Pretty
是的  相当美
Yes, quite
脆弱
Fragile
的确
Indeed
来吧派大星  玩点欢乐的吧
Come on, Patrick, let's do something fun
你是否要进行统计
You want to run some statistics
或是观察现象
or observe phenomenon
并对上述现象作出对应的假设
and render hypothesis of said phenomenon?
我想的更多的是跳绳
I was thinking more like jumping rope
或者单腿赛跑
or one-legged races
[ duck-duck-hermit crab：改自儿童游戏
"duck-duck-goose"，玩法类似于丢手绢 ]
或者一起来玩丢寄居蟹
or playing duck-duck- hermit crab
毫无欢乐之感
Doesn't feel like fun
要不来点笑话
How about some jokes
派大星
Patrick
吉他跟水母有什么区别
What's the difference between a guitar and a jellyfish?
水母不能弹
You can't strum a jellyfish
对
Yes
天啊  这么晚了
Oh, my, look at the time
我真的必须走了
I really must be going
派大星是怎么了
What's wrong with Patrick?
好希望他可以好起来
I sure hope he gets better soon
好点没  派大星
Are you better, Pat?
你在干啥
What are you doing?
只是在研究这种神奇的亚种
Just studying this amazing subspecies
我倒要让你见识什么叫亚种
I'll show you subspecies
要去看章鱼哥吗
Want to visit Squidward?
既然工作业已完成
Since I am finished with my work
我就迎合一下你那琐碎的消遣
I'll humor you in your trivial pursuits
我无论走到哪都能认得出这首曲子
I'd recognize that piece anywhere
科尼利厄斯河豚第67号  郁蓝交响曲
Cornelius Pufferfish's Opus 67, "Symphony in Blue"
派大星
Patrick?
乐曲很动听
It's a beautiful piece
实际演奏仍需用功
Execution needs some work
我建议在稍慢的第7小节处
May I suggest that on the seventh bar
of the adagio andante
让降b琶音力度变为很强
that you add a little fortissimo
on the arpeggiated b-flat scale?
我都没想过要这么演奏
I never thought to do it like that
那是因为你很少思考
Well, that is because you rarely think
你怎么这么懂音乐
How do you know so much about music?
创意的迸发可以提供精神上的解放
A creative outlet provides a spiritual release
以及促进形成健康的心理平衡
and helps facilitate a healthy mental balance
是不是还包括边打嗝边讲话
Does that include belch talking?
海绵宝宝先生  你的幽默甚是庸俗
Mr. SquarePants, I find your humor vulgar
我都不知道你知识这么渊博  派大星
I had no idea you were so knowledgeable, Patrick
你可不可以当我的音乐导师
Do you think you could be my musical mentor?
各位
Guys?
我们从头开始
Let's take it from the top
表现不太优秀  章鱼哥
Not so excellent, Squidward
我来为你演示恰当的吹奏技术
Let me demonstrate the proper technique
经过再三的考虑  熟能生巧
On second thought, practice makes perfect
开始
Let's begin
谢谢你  我的好小子
Thank you, my good chap
不幸的是  这首曲子仅供竖笛独奏用
Unfortunately this is a solo piece for clarinet only
一二三四
And one, two, three, four
停
Stop
够了
Enough
自己去找新导师
Find yourself a new mentor
既然你有空了  我们去吃东西吧
Now that you have some free time, let's get some grub
海绵宝宝  恐怕不行
No, SpongeBob, I'm afraid not
我这有一瓶全新的超多泡的泡泡水
Well, I have a brand new bottle
of super bubbly bubble soap
不必  再次谢谢
No, thanks again
那也许等会可以扮海盗玩
Maybe later we can play pirates
我亲爱的海绵宝宝  没用的
Robert, my dear, it's no use
我们渐行渐远了
We've just grown apart
什么
What?
你这是什么意思
What do you mean?
我知道我们过去曾经欢乐过
I know we've had fun in the past
可我们无法再兼容下去了
but we're just not compatible anymore
是时候应该分道扬镳了
It's time we went our separate ways
这就是人生
Such is life
可派大星  你是我最好的朋友
But Patrick, you're my best friend
我知道难以接受
I know it's hard
但请你振作  老兄
but brace up, chap
好
Yeah
也许我们将来某一天会再次重逢
Maybe our paths will cross again some day
请你勿忘我  海绵宝宝先生
Think fondly of me, Mr. SquarePants
再见
Good-bye
最好的朋友先生
Mr. Best Friend
珊迪  你在吗
Sandy, you there?
我需要一点专业协助
I need some professional help
派大星
Patrick?
派大星  你的全新样子可以得A+了
Well, Pat, the new you gets an "A" plus
谢谢  珊迪
Why, thank you, Sandra
我发现你的智慧也同样饶有趣味
I find your intellect rather stimulating as well
真的吗
Really?
谢了
Thanks
那派大星  你觉得这题要怎么解
Well, Patrick, what do you think about this problem?
只要将某一系数的形式进行转换
You simply change the literal term to a coefficient
则可通过被减数得到所求的商
and the minuend will achieve the desired quotient
连构造最简单的哺乳动物
Even the simplest of mammals
略微思考都可以解出来
could figure it out with a little thought
你那几个意思  派大星
What do you mean by that, Patrick?
我仅仅是认为
I'm merely suggesting
这种方程亟需补习  而你却无能解开
you lack the ability to solve remedial equations
你是在说我傻吗
Are you suggesting I'm dumb?
我会用更高级的词汇来形容  就比如
I'd use a more sophisticated word like
有缺陷
"impaired"
我看你最好该走人了
I think you'd better leave
我仅仅是在帮忙
I was only trying to help
我才用不着你这种帮忙  大懂哥
I don't need your kind of help, Mr. Know-It-All
我更喜欢从前那个弱智的你
I liked you better when you were a barnaclehead
从来没想过我会失去最好的朋友
I never thought I'd lose my best friend
我又能如何争得过天才
How can I compete with geniuses?
虽然我满腹经纶  却无人可以共享
Surrounded by knowledge and no one to share it with
无人与我相伴
no one I can call friend
曾经与我欢笑的那个人是谁
Who's that old chap I used to run with?
我的朋友海绵宝宝
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob
我的朋友派大星
至少派大星还是我记忆中的朋友
At least Patrick's my friend in my memories
美好的过去
The glory days
为何渐行渐远
Why have we grown apart?
我必须运用我所有的学识解开这问题
I must apply all that I know to solve this problem
欢乐学
那会是什么
What could it be?
有什么区别
What's different?
有什么
What?
我愿付出一切  让昔日好友重回身边
I'd do anything
to have my old buddy back by my side again
来了
Coming
派大星
Patrick--
你是在绑架我吗
you're kidnapping me?
是的
Yes, I am
好耶
咱该干啥
What should we do?
我们要找回欢乐  无论代价如何
We are going to have fun, whatever the cost may be
那就来吧
Let's do this
好  我们来找回欢乐
Yes, let's have some fun
好耶
Oh, yeah
绝对没错
Absolutely
确定能让我发觉这种活动是欢乐的吗
Are you quite sure I found this activity to be fun?
确定
Yeah
是不是很欢乐啊  派大星
That was fun, huh, Patrick?
欢乐是何时消失的  海绵宝宝
When did the fun go away, SpongeBob?
是在你跳下那座悬崖
It went away when you jumped off that cliff
头撞没之后消失的
and knocked your head clean off
对了
That's it
咋了
That's what?
派大星  你要干什么
Patrick, what are you doing?
我要重复我在那天的动作
I'm going to duplicate my actions from that day
悬崖危险
查明我变化的源头
to ascertain the origin of my chaannge
派大星
Patrick
坚持住  兄弟
Hold on, buddy
行了
There you go
放心  派大星
Don't worry, Patrick
上次能找回你的头  这次肯定也行
I found your head last time, I'll find it again
不在这后面  不在这下面
Not back there, not under here
万一找不到呢
What if I can't find it?
可怜的无头派大星
Poor headless Patrick
派大星  你的头回来了
Patrick, your head is back
可是
But
觉得哪不一样没
do you feel different?
实际上毫无变化
Quite unchanged, actually
看来再也无法一同欢乐了
I guess we'll never have fun together again
你说你上次找到了我被移除的头颅
You said you found my dislodged cranial cap last time
没错
Yes?
你究竟是在哪里找到的
Where exactly did you find it?
本来是在这的
It was right here
不可能
Impossible
若我落在这  我那断头的运动轨迹
If I landed here, the trajectory
of my dismembered skull
末态的位置不是那
would cause it to come to rest not there
而是这  正好在原位置北面五米处
but here, exactly five meters due north
可如果说这是你的头  那我捡到了啥
But if that's your head, then what did I pick up over?
珊瑚脑田
珊瑚脑
Brain coral
怪不得你变这么聪明  兄弟
No wonder you got so smart, buddy
给你  派大星
Here you go, Patrick
你的旧头
your old head
你确定你要放弃知识智慧
Are you sure you want to
give up being smart and phosisticated
只为再当我朋友吗
to be my friend again?
知识智慧无法替代友情
Knowledge can never replace friendship
我宁愿当个白痴
I prefer to be an idiot
你不只是个白痴  派大星
Not just an idiot, Patrick
你还是我朋友
You're also my pal
派大星
Patrick?
说话啊  派大星
Say something, Patrick
嗨  海绵宝宝
Hi, SpongeBob
派大星  你回来了
Patrick, you're back
海章融合
分镜总监
翻译: 1440kHz
编剧
技术总监
动画总监
制片指导
本字幕仅限学习交流
严禁用于商业用途
我爱章鱼哥
章鱼哥  我们爱你
Squidward, we love you
我们爱你  章鱼哥
We love you Squidward
你是我偶像
you're my favorite
好了好了
All right, all right
又是一个丑陋的工作日
Time for another hideous day at work
就再忍一忍吧  帅哥
Just hang in there, gorgeous
你会在明天的竖笛独奏会上大放异彩
Your star will shine at the clarinet recital tomorrow
又是一个超棒的工作日
Time for another glorious day at work
早安  章鱼哥
Good morning, Squidward
今早是不是很美好啊
And isn't it a lovely morning?
你上班路上干嘛吹竖笛啊
Why are you playing the clarinet on your way to work?
我在给我的竖笛演奏会练习
I'm practicing for my clarinet recital
马上  整个裤头村
Soon all of Bikini Bottom
认出我这才子  那就是章鱼哥
will recognize the talent
that is Squidward Tentacles
再见  海绵笨笨
Good-bye, SpongeBoob
蟹堡王见  章鱼哥
See you at the Krusty Krab, Squidward
珊迪
Hey Sandy--
这什么东西
what's this?
这个是我新做的物质瞬移器
Well, this here's my new matter transporter
可以把东西转移到别处去
It can move things from one place to another
时间只要一眨眼
in the blink of an eye
听着高大上
That sounds fancy
给你示范下用法
Let me show you how it works
瞬移器遥控
返回
前进
它到哪去了
Where'd it go?
想到哪就到哪去
Just where you think it would be
我上班要迟到了
I'm late for work
你的机器能把我传送到蟹堡王去吗
Think your machine could zap me over to the Krusty Krab?
我一直很想来个生物来做实验的
Always did want to try a critter
可以  有啥不行的
Sure, why not?
进去吧  海绵宝宝
Get in there, SpongeBob
抓紧了
Hold on tight
珊迪  感觉好
Gee, Sandy, this sure feels
又要上班了
Well, here we go again
章鱼哥
Hey, Thkwidward
这玩意咋的了
What's going on with this thing?
到底咋了
What in tarnation?
嗨  珊迪
Hi, Sandy
不太清楚这怎么回事
I'm not sure what it is
我好像有点不对劲了
but something seems different about me
没错
Yeah--
我也一样
me, too
你在拿我手干什么
What're you doing with my hand?
我
What
我在拿你手干什么
what am I doing with your hand?
这什么玩意
What is this?
我们融合在一起了
We're all mixed up together
太可怕了
This is horrible
我明天还有竖笛演奏会啊
I have my clarinet recital tomorrow
问题不大  章鱼哥
It's not so bad, Squidward
这下能当好兄弟  同甘共苦一辈子了
Now we can be best buddies
and do everything together forever
珊迪  都是你搞的鬼吗
Sandy, was this your doing?
你得把我们分开
You've got to get us separated
我也想知道怎么分
Well, I wish I knew how
那你也得做点什么啊
Well, you have to do something
我可不能跟他粘在一起
I can't stay stuck to him
不知道把你们
I wonder what would happen
用瞬移器传回去会怎么样
if I tried zapping you back in the transporter?
行  好办法
Yeah, good idea--
传吧
let's do it
那就碰碰运气吧
Well, here goes nothing
裤头村小学
同学们  今天是提米的生日
All right, children, today is Timmy's birthday
知道什么意思吧
You know what that means--
准备好了吗  提米
ready, Timmy?
恭喜你  史密斯太太
Congratulations, Mrs. Smith
你生下了一名健康的男婴
You gave birth to a healthy baby boy
能看我宝宝吗
May I see my baby?
当然
Of course
我第一眼看到你  就深深地爱上了你
I've been in love with you
ever since I first laid my eye on you
宝贝  你叫什么名字
Hey, baby, what's your name?
没用的  珊迪
It's no use, Sandy
还是老样子
We're still the same
那就可惜了
Well, that's a darn shame
话说回来
You know what?
我在设计一样全新发明
I was working on the blueprints for a new invention
不过还在雏形阶段
but it's still in the embryonic stage
做什么都行
Try anything
我不能这样子去参加竖笛演奏会
I cannot go to my clarinet recital like this
我会继续研究的
I'll continue working on it
期间你们要乐观点哦
In the meantime, you boys keep your heads up
一辈子在一起
Together forever
苦啊
Misery
海绵宝宝  就没人教过你骑自行车吗
SpongeBob, hasn't anybody taught you how to ride a bike?
放心  会好好开的
Don't worry, I'll drive
蟹堡王
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob
辣酱
我得戒了辣酱
I got to lay off the hot sauce
这里面到底怎么了
What in blazes is going on in here?
蟹老板好
Hi, Mr. Krabs
你们两个无所事事的在干什么
What are you two doing laying around?
快工作去
Get to work
就听你的
If you say so
你们是怎么了
What happened to you?
我不想知道了
I don't want to know
做好你们的工作就是
Just go do your jobs
遵命  老板
Aye, aye, cap'n
你就非要乐于助人当小丑吗
Do you have to be such an accommodating buffoon?
章鱼哥  众所周知我是海绵
Squidward, everybody knows I'm a sponge
一点都不像气球
I look nothing like a balloon
[ buffoon（小丑）与 ballon（气球）谐音 ]
没空扯这个
I don't have time for this
我得去管收银机
I got to man the cash register
此处点餐
要点什么吗
Can I help you?
能来两份蟹黄堡吗
Can I get two Krabby Patties, please?
海绵宝宝  来两份蟹黄堡
SpongeBob, I need two Krabby Patties
两份蟹黄堡马上就来
Two Krabby Patties coming right up
面包够不到
I can't reach the bun
海绵宝宝  这是在磨蹭什么
SpongeBob, what's the hold up?
抱歉  蟹老板
S-sorry, Mr. Krabs
我搞得定
I'm on it
时间就是金钱  小子
Time is money, boy
时间就是金钱  没错
Time is money, right
你好  面包
Hello, bun
我们总算见面了
at last we meet
现在来
And now for
都给我得了
All right, that's it
你们破坏我生意  我都快亏死了
I can't afford you jeopardizing my business
真是成事不足败事有余
You two are more trouble than you're worth
没把这问题解决就不准回来
And don't come back
until you get this problem sorted out
章鱼哥  从好的方面看
Look on the bright side, Squidward
至少我们还有彼此
At least we still have each other
所以我们一开始才那样陷入这番窘境
That's how we got in this predicament in the first place
你个白痴
You imbecile
先失陪一下  我要静一静
Now, if you'll excuse me, I'd like a moment of peace
酷啊  怪咖老哥
Rock on, freaky bro
珊迪
Sandy
快说你已经想到分开我们的办法了
Please tell me you've figured out a way to separate us
跟分子分离射线枪打个招呼吧
Say hello to the molecular separator ray
分子分离射线枪
你好啊  分子分离射线枪
Hello, molecular separator ray
那就开始干正事吧
Well, let's get on with it
明晚就是我竖笛演奏会了
My clarinet recital is tomorrow night
那个  我还没有完全做好
Well, I'm not quite done with it yet
你说什么
What'd you say?
我还在组装它
I'm still putting it together
最快的话我会
At best I'll have it ready
后天弄好吧
day a2fter tomorrow maybe?
什么
What?
要到后天
Day after tomorrow?
不行不行不行
No, no, no, no
我明天还有演出
I have a performance tomorrow
可不能粘着那个黄色怪咖
I can't be stuck to that yellow freak
珊迪  求你了
Sandy, please--
一定要在演奏会之前就做好
you got to do it before the show
那个
Well
我看
I suppose
你明天上台之前我就做好
I'll have it ready before you go on
果然
Of course
活动中心隆重介绍
章鱼哥
天啊
Oh, my
珊迪  你在哪儿
Where are you Sandy?
珊迪
Sandy?
我做不到  我上不了台
I can't do it, I can't go out there
章鱼哥
Squidward
这一刻属于你
this is your moment
你会塑造传说
the story you will tell
待到你再回忆此刻  你已成为
when you look back as a
超级巨星
superstar
Superstar?
快上台给他们瞧瞧
Now go out there and give them
他们所看过的最好表演
the best darned show they've ever seen
说得对
You're right--
表演必须继续
the show must go on
女士们先鱼们
Ladies and gentlefish
裤头村社区活动中心
Bikini Bottom's community rec center
隆重介绍  章鱼哥
is proud to present Squidward Tentacles
老公  我好怕
Honey, I'm scared
嗨
Hi
酷啊  怪咖老哥
Rock on, freaky bro
他们真的好喜欢
They really liked it
继续啊  章鱼哥
There you go, Squiddy
他们
They
they
他们在喝彩
they're cheering
超级巨星
Superstardom--
肯定就是这种感觉
this must be what it feels like
就是这种模样
This is what it looks like
这种
what it
声音
sounds like
还有
and
这种味道
what it smells like
简直让我陶醉
Simply intoxicating
你们在这啊
Well, there you boys are
看来我正好及时
Looks like I'm just in time
珊迪
Sandy?
分子分离射线枪这么一射
One blast of this molecular separator ray
你们就能永久分离了
and you'll be separated for good
不要  等下
No, no wait--
珊迪  先别射
Sandy, don't
我觉得我要吐了
I think I'm going to be sick
老子要走人了
I'm out of here
不要  别走
No, wait
别走
wait
真是的
Come on
我这么个名气时刻没了
My one moment of fame gone
肯定有什么办法可以倒回来
There's got to be some way to reverse this
别乱碰  章鱼哥
No, Squidward
那可是非常敏感的装置
that's a very sensitive device
章鱼哥  我不会
Squidward, I wouldn't
请问你有什么毛病  章鱼哥先生
So, what seems to be the problem, Mr. Tentacles?
我一生下来就有这毛病了
It all started when I was born